Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is כ' Chaf בבא
בתרא, Bava Batra, excuse me 20, and we pick up with
מיתיבי Maysivay four lines from the top of כ' עמוד א'. Chaf
Amud Aleph. We're in the middle of dealing with a statement that
was made in the middle of the previous דף daf where in
the name of שמואל, Shmuel, רב טובי בר קיסנא Rav Tuvi bar
Kisna said in the name of שמואל Shmuel that if you have
like a wafer in a window, it does not reduce the size
of the window. What that means is if that is an opening
in a wall of a טפח tefach and there's טומאה tumah dead
body in one room, then the rules of אוהל ohel for dead
bodies will bring the טומאה tumah into the next room if the
window is a טפח. tefach. However, if it's less than a טפח
tefach then it won't. And let's say the window is a טפח
tefach but because of this wafer the now, if you would start
from the top of the wafer, that's the thin wafer in the
window, it would not be a טפח tefach high or wide. So
the statement in the name of שמואל Shmuel was that will, that
is not considered relevant, the fact that the wafer is there because
you will eventually want to remove the wafer in order to eat
it. Okay so this is a teaching that when we assess the
width of the, you know, of the window it has to be
something that you really are or the height, something that you really
are planning on leaving there in order to, if we want it
to reduce the height of the window. And this we'll see why
this is brought in, תוספות Tosafot points out it's brought in because
part of the conversation will get to the idea about various vegetation.
Is it good for a wall, bad for a wall? Which ties
into our משנה Mishnah about distancing the vegetation from the wall. Okay
so let's take a look. We pick up with four lines from
the top of כ' עמוד א'. Chaf Amud Aleph. מיתיבי. Maysivay. I'll
challenge this, this position of שמואל. Shmuel. עשבים Asavim and here you
go grass שתלשן והניחן בחלון shetalahan venichan bechalon that you ripped them
out of the ground and you put them in a window that
is conjoined, connected two
rooms, או שעלו מאליהן בחלונות o she'alu meyalehen bechalonot or that they
themselves you know popped up in the wall, imagine you know you
got a wall made out of stone and there's grass growing between
the gaps in the stone and now there's grass in the window
that just got there on its own,
ומטליות שאין בהן שלוש על שלוש umetlanyot she'ein bahem shalosh al shalosh
or rags that do not have three by three fingerbreadths. Very important
to pay attention to whether the word is by שלוש shalosh is
שלוש shalosh or שלושה shelosha or ארבע arba or ארבעה. arba'ah. It's
שלוש shalosh and ארבע arba אצבעות etzbaot so if it's שלוש על
שלוש shalosh al shalosh that's fingerbreadths. If it's שלושה shelosha or ארבעה
arba'ah then it's טפחים. tefachim. That's just grammar but that's really critical.
We're going to see in a minute a four by four which
is four by four טפחים tefachim but this is three by three
fingerbreadths so about three by three inches. Alright and the הלכה halacha
is that if you have a rag that's less than that size
it's not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. All of these are things that
are not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because the principle is that something
that is susceptible for טומאה tumah it does not close up the
window, it does not minimize the height or the width of the
window. So all of these are going to be a list of
things that are not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. A rag less than
three by three fingerbreadths. והאיבר והבשר המדולדלין בבהמה ובחיה veahayver vehabasar hamedulalin
bibeheimah uvechayah and if you have some flesh or limb that is
like hanging on, partially hanging on in an animal. An animal got
a finger let's say you know or an arm dislocated shoulder it
was ripped from it by another animal but it's still it's still
connected but it's only half connected and that's in the in the
window. So because it is still not yet completely disconnected it's so
it is not מקבל
טומאה. mekabel tumah. ועוף ששכן בחלון veof sheshachan bechalon or a bird
that is just nesting, resting in the window. Also live animal not
מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. ועובד כוכבים שישב בחלון veoveid kochavim sheyashav bechalon
or a non-Jew who sitting in the window and a non-Jew even
though rabbinically it's a source of טומאה tumah דאורייתא d'oraiaita he's not
מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. ובן שמונה המונח בחלון uben shemonah hamunach bechalon
and if you have a baby that was born in the eighth
month, the rabbis thought that a baby born in the eighth month
will definitely die. So therefore it is not, it's considered like a
stone, like you know, and therefore not now he's not dead yet
for if he's dead yet it would be the source of טומאה.
tumah. But it's not while so while it's alive it's not a
live in the sense of a human being that we don't assume
that it will live a human life you know so therefore it
does not have the status of a human being who is מקבל
טומאה. mekabel tumah. One day old infant is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
but this which is a one day old infant or whatever it
is but assume that it will die very soon you know and
does not have the capacity I should say to live does not
have that status. And והמלח vhamelach and salt וכלי חרס vekli cheres
and a clay vessel and pottery, now pottery's going to be interesting
because normally pottery is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah we discussed that before
but only through its opening, so it would have to be that
the opening
is facing the opposite direction, not towards the room where the dead
body is. And salt, even though you add salt to food, it
is not a food on itself, so it's not מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah. וספר תורה veSefer Torah and a Sefer Torah; okay, it's a,
you know, it's a very powerful idea, right? Torah is not מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tumah, but it's really the fact that it's just a
book, and a book does not satisfy any of the requirements of
a כלי kli of a vessel to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah.
All of those things כולם ממעטין בחלון, kulam mematin bechalon, they all
shrink the size, you know, make the size, the height of the
window less. If they're in the window, you would measure the טפח
tefach by טפח, tefach, you would treat them as if they were
part of the wall, and you'd measure the טפח tefach by טפח
tefach from the top of them to the top of the window.
And that is because these are things that are not מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah. However, goes on to say, you know, this is a
תוספתא Tosefta in אהלות Ohalos and it goes on to say the
following: אבל השלג והברד והגליד והכפור, Aval hasheleg vehabarad vehagalid vehakefor, but
if you're dealing with snow or hail or frost
or, you know, frost like a different type of frost, והמים vehamayim
or water, כולם אין ממעטין בחלון, kulam ein mematin bechalon, they do
not. Now it is not because, you know, water is food and
is מקבל טומאה; mekabel tumah; that wouldn't apply, you know, that could
be true, but it wouldn't apply to the snow or the frost
unless you were planning on eating it, and even, you know, random
rainwater, if you're not, if it's not water that's intentional, intending to
eat it, it's not considered yet food to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah. So the reason though these things are not ממעיט בחלון mameit
bechalon is because they're not going to stay there, they will just
naturally melt away, okay? Or flow away. כולם אין ממעטין בחלון, kulam
ein mematin bechalon, so they do not minimize the size. Okay, so
these are things that, you know, the that are, even though obviously
something that's מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah would not shrink the size of
the window, but even these that are not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
are not because they're just going to melt away. Okay, now we're
going to go through this whole list because it seems like the
only thing that bothers the תוספתא Tosefta is the question about whether
it is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah and will just naturally physically stay
there on its own. It seems that it's completely unconcerned with the
question of whether you will plan to take it away. And it
seems that that's not a relevant factor, although for שמואל, Shmuel, that
was key: if you plan to take it away, it does not
shrink the size. So then why are all these things, why do
they shrink the size? So let's take a look; we'll go through
them one by one. והעשבים חזו לבהמה, veha'asavim chazu lebehemah, grass, you
would, if you had grass in your window, you would take it
out and you'd feed it to your animal. So that should then
therefore according to שמואל Shmuel not count to shrink the size of
the window. באפרזתא, be'afrazta, that you're talking with a type of a
grass that's like poisonous, okay, and therefore you're not going to feed
it to your animal. Okay, let's go to the next line. או
שעלו מאליהם, o she'alu me'aleihem, or there's grass that's like growing from
the ground and in between the stones. So the גמרא Gemara says:
one minute, כיון דקשי לכותל, keivan dekashi lekotel, since it's difficult to
the wall, this is why we're bringing it in, because our משנה
Mishnah spoke about distancing things from the wall that are growing near
it that would cause it damage. שקלי להו, shaklei lehu, you obviously
would plan to remove it, so why should it be ממעיט בחלון?
mameit bechalon? So אמר רבא: Amar Rava: בכותל חורבה, bekotel churva, we're
dealing with a wall that is in a, you know, desolate area
that nobody cares about; it's ownerless. You know, you might have a
destroyed like a house that's been abandoned, so nobody is planning on
removing the grass because nobody... there's a dead body in one room,
and the question is stuff in the other room, or people the
other room, does the טומאה tumah go through the window? But nobody
cares about the grass because nobody, nobody owns it. רב פפא אמר:
Rav Pappa amar: אפילו בכותל יישוב, afilu bekotel yishuv, no, even if
it's a wall in a settled area and, you know, people do
care that the wall should be in a good state. בבאין חוץ
לשלשה לחלון, beva'in chutz leshloshah lechalon, they are growing on the ground,
they're not popping up through the stones, they're growing on the ground
three away, like our משנה, Mishnah, you have to keep it three
טפחים tefachim away so that it doesn't damage. So they're growing from
the ground is not a danger to the wall, and it's very,
very high grass and this tall grass that grows up and then
it falls over and it now is, you know, falling on top
of the, you know, bending and leaning inside the window, but it
is not damaging it because it is not growing near the wall
at all, and that's why you're willing to leave it there. Okay,
so מטלניות, matlaniyot, so the גמרא Gemara says: okay, let's go to
the rags that are less than three by three fingerbreadths. חזו לקריא
ללבושא, chazu lekarya lelevusha, you can still use it to patch up
a tear in your garment, so you can use it as a
patch. Now you might say, if you can use it as a
patch, why is it so insignificant that it's not מקבל טומאה? mekabel
tumah? מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? But it's not the normal type of
thing that people would like, you know, save and be מצניע matzniya
and put away in storage, okay, but saying that you're not going
to, it's not significant enough for you to like make a point
of holding on to it, does not mean that you, you know,
would it use it at all if it was available to you.
So the גמרא Gemara says why aren't we concerned that somebody, you
know, might want to take it to use it as a patch?
So בשמיכתא, b'smichta, you're dealing with it's thick and it won't serve
well as a patch. All right? So then it says, where are
we, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
חזו לאומנא, chazu l'umna, it's still fit for a blood letter, you
can still use it to like wipe away the blood when he
does his bloodletting. So בבריסקא, b'riska, you're dealing with a scratchy one
and therefore you don't want to use it on somebody's skin. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי בבריסקא ei b'riska or בריסקא briska really
means sackcloth, but the point is it's scratchy. אי בבריסקא, ei b'riska,
so one minute, if it's sackcloth, so then by sackcloth, to not
be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, it's not less than three by three
fingerbreadths, שאין בה שלש על שלש, she'ein bah shalosh al shalosh, it
shouldn't be the definition of less than three by three to be
not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, שאין בהן ארבעה על ארבעה, she'ein bahen
arba'ah al arba'ah,
it should be enough that it's less than four by four טפחים,
tefachim, because it's ארבעה, arba'ah, that's how you know. Anyway, so by
sackcloth, you know, normal types of fabric, if you can use it,
you can use it for patches, you can use it for other
things. Sackcloth, unless it's large, nobody's going to, it doesn't have any
other use than to use for a type of a sack. So
anything less than four by four טפחים, tefachim, like about a foot
by a foot, would not be considered significant. So clearly we're not
dealing with sackcloth in the משנה Mishna because the משנה Mishna said
that it's not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah when it's less than three
by three fingerbreadths. So the גמרא Gemara מיבעי ליה, mibaei lei, it
should have said four by four if it's sackcloth. No, כעין בריסקא,
k'ein briska, no, we mean like a sackcloth that it's scratchy. So
you're dealing with a little piece of a cloth that you have
no interest in and you would not want to use, and therefore
you don't have intent to remove it. והאיבר והבשר המדולדלין בבהמה ובחיה,
v'ha'eiver v'habasar hamiduldalin bivheimah uvchayah, so if you've got this limb dangling
from an animal that's in the window, so what do you mean,
according to שמואל, Shmuel, that's not going to stay there? ערקא ואזלא,
arka v'azla, the בהמה beheimah will like uproot it and go, meaning
the בהמה beheimah is just going to walk away. So בקשורה, bikshurah,
no, the animal is tied down. Now even if the animal's tied
down, like, you know, is it slim tied down? You have to
imagine a scenario where it would not naturally remove its limb from
the window. Very, very hard. I mean let's just face it, the
גמרא Gemara is making this תוספתא Tosefta a whole string of אוקימתות,
okimtose, a whole string of special circumstances, so it shouldn't, you know,
in order to defend שמואל's Shmuel's position, but obviously the פשט pshat
here is completely against שמואל, Shmuel, that it doesn't matter if something
is going to be removed or not, it still minimizes the width
of the window. But this is the גמרא, Gemara, it's place, it's
creating these very unusual circumstances to say that we're talking about a
case where you're not planning on removing it, okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says בקשורה, bikshurah, the animal is bound. So the גמרא Gemara
says שחיט לה, shachit leh, so, so what? You know, you're still
going to, you would still, I mean eventually you would want to
shecht the animal and eat it for the food and then you
would take all the meat away and you would take it away.
You're not just going to leave your animal there forever. So the
גמרא Gemara says בטמאה, bitmeiah, we're dealing with a non-kosher animal, it's
a mule, let's say. מזבין לה לנכרי, mizbin leh l'nochri, okay, again,
but why are you not going to leave it there forever? You'll
do something with it, you'll sell it to a non-Jew. I don't
know why it doesn't say you'll use it for yourself, but whatever.
בכחושה, bichshusha, all right, it's very weak and it's thin and nobody's
interested in buying it. You got this dying animal with its limb
in the window, you can't do anything with it and therefore you
don't plan on doing anything with it. So the גמרא Gemara says
פסיק שדי לה לכלבי, pasik shadi leh l'chalbei, I don't get it,
says the גמרא, Gemara, you know, why wouldn't you want to like
chop off that limb and throw it to a dog for dog
food? No, כיון דאיכא צער בעלי חיים לא עביד, keivan d'ika tza'ar
ba'alei chayim lo avid, since it will cause pain to animals and
the animal, you wouldn't do it, apparently presumably that would be more
painful than keeping the limb on. Now it's interesting, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that you're not allowed to do it, it gets into
a whole question of צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, is it
דאורייתא, d'oraisa, is it דרבנן, d'rabanan, are you allowed to inflict צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim when you're doing it for the sake
for human purposes? The actual, the general פסק psak of the פוסקים,
poskim, starting with the תרומת הדשן, Trumas Hadeshen, that צער בעלי חיים
tza'ar ba'alei chayim is permissible when it's serving human, you know, human
ends. So here, to use it for dog food, it would be
permissible. But it's not saying it's אסור, assur, it's just saying, well,
it's not your plan, you wouldn't do
it. Okay, so you're going to just leave it there. Again, bizarre
scenario that you're going to leave the animal with its limb in
the window and you'll leave it there forever, you're not planning on,
you know, letting the animal go away or anything. Okay, או ששכן
בחלון. o sheshachan bachalon. Okay, so a bird that is nesting, that,
you know, took up root, like is sitting in the window. פרח
ואזיל, parach v'azil, the גמרא Gemara says that's going to fly away.
בקשור, bikshur, no, you got it tied down. The word ששכן sheshachan
does not sound like you are captured it, it sounds like it
happens to have
Alighted, you know, it happens to have like sort of
stopped, you know, just taken up its residence there, not that you
are tying it down. But that's the case the גמרא Gemara says.
שחיט ליה, shachit lei, okay, but eventually you'll want to use it,
you'll shecht it to eat to eat it, so again it's not
going to stay there. בטמא, betame, it's a non-kosher bird. So you
have no interest in doing that. מזבני ליה לנכרי, mazbenei lei lenochri,
okay, but I mean you want you'll want to do something with
it, you got a captured bird, sell it to a
non-Jew. בכלניסא, bekalanisa, no, we're dealing with this bird, a כלניסא, kalanisa,
whatever type of bird that was, that was a רש״י Rashi says
like it was very thin and you know nobody would have any
use for it. I don't know why you bothered tying it up
if nobody would have any use for it. Maybe you wanted to
use it as an alarm clock or
something. Anyway, יהבי ליה לינוקא, yahvei lei lyanuka, okay, says the גמרא,
Gemara, but still why don't you take it out of the window,
you'll want to use it and give it to your kid as
a pet. במסרית, bimsarit, so the גמרא, Gemara, it's a bird that
scratches, so there's again no use for it. You happen to have
it tied up in the window, why you tied it up who
knows, but there's absolutely no use for it so you're going to
leave it there and that's why it's ממעיט בחלון. memayit bechalon. So
the גמרא Gemara says כלניסא לא מסרטא, kalanisa lo masreta, one minute,
this כלניסא kalanisa bird we know doesn't scratch. כעין כלניסא, keein kalanisa,
no, no, we mean something like it, a scratchy bird that you
would have no, nobody would be interested in buying. All right, so
that's a very, very highly special scenario and that's what the תוספתא
Tosefta was talking about in order to make this work with
שמואל Shmuel's
statement. The גמרא Gemara says ועובד כוכבים שיושב בחלון, ve'oved kochavim sheyoshev
bechalon, so now let's move on in the תוספתא, Tosefta, a non-Jew
sitting in the window. So the גמרא Gemara says קאי ואזיל, kai
ve'azil, he'll get up and go. בכפות, bekafut, again, he's bound
there. אתי חבריה ושרי ליה, atei chavreia vesharei lei, okay, but his
friend will come, see that he's bound up, and he will come
and undo it for him. במצורע, bimtzora, we're talking about a מצורע,
metzora, a leper. Now, this is not the מצורע, metzora, again, it's
a non-Jew of the פסוקים, pesukim, but this is somebody that actually
has a communicable disease and therefore nobody will want to get close
to him. So the גמרא Gemara says אתי מצורע חבריה ושרי ליה,
atei mtzora chavreia vesharei lei, so okay, but at least another מצורע
metzora will come, his friend, and try to help him out and
undo his bonds. אלא בחבושי מלכות, ela bechavushei malchut, fine, fine, fine,
we're not talking about he just happens to be bound up, he
has been, you know, tied up there from the government and they
are holding him prisoner there, and maybe that's his prison to sit
in the window. Don't exactly understand the exact scenario, and therefore he
is, he's stuck there and nobody is allowed to remove him. So
that's it basically, you got a case of a prison with a
non-Jew who's chained up in a window, that's the scenario. Okay. ובן
שמונה המונח בחלון, uven shmonah hamunach bechalon, so now you got this
baby born in the eighth month that's in the window. So the
גמרא Gemara says אתיא אימיה ודריא ליה, atya imei vedarya lei, his
mother will come and remove him. בשבת, beShabbat, no, we're talking about
it's on שבת, Shabbat, דתניא בן שמונה הרי הוא כאבן, detanya ben
shmonah harei hu ke'even, somebody born in the, a baby born in
the eighth month is like a stone, meaning the גמרא Gemara assumes
it's not
likely, we assume it's going to
die, the baby, ואסור לטלטלו בשבת, ve'assur letaltelo beShabbat, and so much
so that it's מוקצה muktzeh and you're not allowed to move it
on שבת. Shabbat. Now, I should just say that
אבל אמו שוחה עליו ומניקתו, aval imo shochah alav umenikato, but a
mother can lean over so that the baby can nurse. מפני הסכנה,
mipnei hasakanah, because of the סכנה. sakanah. Interesting question, what's the סכנה
sakanah if the baby, if we're assuming the baby is going to
die? It's okay, but it's חיי שעה, chay sha'at, it's still life
for a short period of time, anyway but that's quite interesting, that
מפני הסכנה. mipnei hasakanah. Or is it talking about the סכנה sakanah
of the mother if she's not nursing him? There's a lot to
talk about here that's not directly for our topic, but what I
should say is that this הלכה halachah is not where we stop
by this baby born in the eighth month. I was born in
the eighth month, you know, basically פוסקים poskim say they wouldn't say
the גמרא Gemara got the science wrong, but they'll say you know
nowadays things have changed, either physical nature has changed or our technology
has changed, and therefore ברוך השם baruch Hashem even babies born in
the eighth month live and these גמרות Gemaras do not apply. But
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying and therefore since it's שבת
Shabbat you're not allowed to move the baby. Now תוספות Tosafos says,
but you'll move the baby after שבת, Shabbat, you know, so your
baby is still not going to be staying there forever. So the
גמרא Gemara says it must, so תוספות Tosafos says it must be
a case
where you're expecting the baby to die on שבת Shabbat and therefore
you're just going to leave the baby there, there are no plans
to remove the baby. Pretty horrific. Anyway, okay. ומלח, umelach, salt. So
the גמרא Gemara says חזי ליה, chazi lei, next case of the
תוספתא. Tosefta. I don't get it, says the גמרא, Gemara, why can't
you your plant your salt is usable, won't you want to remove
it? So it says
חזי ליה, chazi lei, so the גמרא Gemara says במרירתא, bemarirata, it's
bitter salt, so you don't have a good use for it. So
the גמרא Gemara says חזי לאורוס, chazi le'oros, you can still but
still you would use it for tanning leather. דאית ביה קוצי, de'it
bei kotzei, it's got thistles in it and therefore it's really not
usable. כיוון דקשי לכותל שקלי ליה, kevan dekashei lechotal shakli lei, so
the גמרא Gemara says okay but salt on the wall. going to
be bad for the wall here again we get to things that
are bad for the wall so you'll want to remove it for
that for that reason.
דיספא חספא deyaspa chasba it's sitting on a piece of pottery it's
not directly touching the wall so it's not eating away at the
wall. Gemara says חספא גופא תיחץ chaspa gufa teichatz so that's a
piece of pottery now you know be a chatzitza so the salt
I mean why are we only focusing on the salt if the
only scenario is that the salt is on the pottery then we
should say that the pottery itself will also serve as a you
know to minimize the size of the of the
window. Gemara says דלית ביה שיעורא deleis bei shiura it's not it
doesn't have it's not a it's not a big enough piece of
pottery to have any halachic significance. And therefore and let's read the
mishna כדתנן חרס kedisnan cheres what is the size of a piece
of a pottery shard that you're chayav if you took it out
on
Shabbos? כדי ליתן בין פצים לחבירו. kedai litein bein patzim lachaveiro. It
has to be big enough that you're going to be put it
before like stacked beams you know so that the beams don't warp
and that they stay a little you know air between them. So
therefore it's such a tiny piece that it has absolutely no use.
Of course Tosafot doesn't like this. I mean we also had something
before also that wasn't meaningful for Shabbos the patch that's less than
three by three but that still shrinks the size of the window.
So if the case of salt is only when it's salt on
a piece on a pottery shard even if the pottery shard is
not normally usable for Shabbos purposes why doesn't the pottery shard come
and you know be considered significant enough to shrink the size of
the window? So Tosafot explains the following. Tosafot says hold on let
me. So Tosafot says we're talking about a case where the pottery
shard is so thin that it won't be able to get the
window less than a tefach. So that's why the Baraita didn't talk
about it which is pretty funny you know how do you know
that's exactly the scenario we're talking about? Okay whatever. But then so
therefore we only focused on the salt. But then why did we
quote this mishna in Shabbos? Because to say but still won't you
remove the pottery shard to use the pottery shard and by removing
the pottery shard you'll also remove the salt? So why are you
leaving the salt there? So it says no we're talking about a
pottery shard that's so small in terms of its width and area
you know that you have no use for it so you'll just
leave it there and that's why you'll leave the salt there it
has no use the pottery shard has no use you'll just leave
it there we didn't mention the pottery shard because it was so
thin to be insignificant. All right. So now the Gemara says כלי
חרס. kli cheres. So now it went on to speak about if
it's a pottery not just a pottery shard but an actual you
know pottery vessel. So again if it's in the window in a
way in which the mouth is facing not into the room where
the dead body is so that's not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So
the Gemara says okay but how about the fact that you're going
to remove it? חזי ליה chazi lei that's something that's fit for
you. דמיטנף demitneif no it's it's disgusting it's got soiled and it's
not usable. חזי לאומנא chazi leumna so what? A bloodletter can use
it you know for for where to let the blood
into. דמינקיב deminkav it's got a hole in it so again it's
a pottery vessel that's not really usable and you're just going to
leave it there. ספר תורה sefer torah now how about a Sefer
Torah? Oh my god if there's anything that you would
remove. חזי למקרא chazi lemikra it's fit for reading. בבלאי beviloi no
it's all worn out and it's no longer usable. Okay so the
Gemara says והא בעי גניזה veha bei gnizah okay but then you
would have to you know put it away bury it treat it
properly. So how can you leave it in the
window? שמה גניזתו shama gnizaso no that'll be the gnizah you don't
have to do gnizah underground that's its permanent place of resting and
that's the same way and that's sort of considered respectful treatment you're
going to leave it there. Again I don't know why it's respectful
treatment if it's in a window open to everybody and open to
the elements I mean obviously something in gnizah is going to disintegrate
but still that is an interesting discussion you know within the gnizah
that that could even count as a gnizah. But basically we had
a whole Tosefta that pretty much every single case seemed like something
you would remove and it said that it shrinks the size of
the window and in order to make it consistent with Shmuel's position
we made a whole slew of special cases and circumstances to be
scenarios in which you would not want to remove it. Okay now
we are moving on. אמר רב amar rav Rav said
בכל עושין מחיצה חוץ ממלח ורבב bechol osin mechitza chutz memelach verevav
you can make a mechitza for let's say Shabbos purposes you know
to be make something considered a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid not the
mechitzas we have in shul the Gemara never discusses that but you
can make a mechitza for like sukkah purposes Shabbos purposes from anything
except from salt and revav is like fat why because those things
are you know won't be permanent the salt will scatter even though
you got a pile of salt or whatever it's it's going to
it won't stay there and the fat will dissolve. Okay, so even
though it sort of has some shape now, it won't last. So
הלכתית, halachically, that won't count as a מחיצה, mechitza, as a wall
for שבת. shabbos. ושמואל אמר אפילו מחיצה, u'Shmuel amar afilu mechitza, ושמואל
אמר אפילו מלח. u'Shmuel amar afilu melach. No, you can use
salt. אמר פפא ולא פליגי, Amar Pappa v'lo peligi, they really not
debating. הא במלח סדומית הא במלח אסטרוקנית. Ha b'melach Sedomis ha b'melach
Istronknis. Okay, they're talking about two different types of salt. One is
talking about מלח סדומית, melach Sedomis, which is mineral salt, you know,
we all, it's like מלח סדומית melach Sedomis is discussed by מים
אחרונים mayim acharonim and it gets on this whole like mystical idea
about it, and but basically it's talking about mineral salt. And the
other one is, or you know, is sea salt. So, and apparently
the idea is is that the mineral salt is, you know, is
hard, right? Especially if you cut it out of the, you know,
of the, what do you call it? out of the, you know,
out of the ground. So that is a salt that will count
as a מחיצה, mechitza, and the other is sea salt, which is
more granular or whatever, and that's one that will not count as
a מחיצה mechitza because it will not keep its form. Now and
then the גמרא Gemara says like this: והשתא דאמר רבה, V'hashta d'amar
Rabbah, now now that Rabbah said, עושה אדם שני ציבורי מלח ומניח
עליהם קורה שהמלח מעמדת את הקורה והקורה מעמדת את המלח, oseh adam
shenei tziburei melach u'maniach aleihem korah shehamelach ma'amedes es hakorah vehakorah ma'amedes
es hamelach, that if you want to have a צורת הפתח, tzuras
hapethach, you know, for an עירוב eruv or for the opening of
a מבוי mavoi on שבת, shabbos, and you want to have, you
know, a חצר, chatzer, whatever, one could get into the specifics there.
Anyway, and you want to have, you know, a קורה, korah, a
pole, you know, a לחי וקורה. lechi v'korah. So what you can
do is, you know, posts and then something on top of them.
So you can use two mounds of salt for your posts, and
you can put on them a beam. Why? Because the salt holds
up the beam, so it serves the proper purpose there, and therefore
that's considered, you know, you know, that part of the צורת הפתח,
tzuras hapethach, and the beam by its weight pressure and pushes down
and keeps the salt in its place. So now that we have
a scenario that can function like that, that the salt will be
kept in its place with the beam, so now we say, okay,
where are
we? והקורה מעמדת את המלח. vehakorah ma'amedes es hamelach. אפילו מלח אסטרוקנית,
Afilu melach Istronknis, even sea salt can work. ולא פליגי, V'lo peligi,
and they don't
disagree. הא דאיכא קורה הא דליכא קורה. Ha d'ika korah ha d'leika
korah. The difference will be is there a beam on top of
it or not a beam on top of it. Okay, so that
was wrapping up, you know, because we had mentioned salt and walls,
so I think that sort of why we wrapped up this discussion
here about מחיצות. mechitzas. Finishing up the next part of the משנה.
mishna. מרחיקין את הריחיים ג' מן השכב שהן ד' מן הרכב. Marchikin
es harechayim gimel min hashechev shehein daled min harechev. You distance the,
the, what, the mill. It has to be three טפחים tefachim away
from the שכב, shechev, the base of the mill, which is four
טפחים tefachim
away
from
הרכב, harechev, the middle part of it which is wider. So the
middle part of it protrudes a טפח tefach and therefore it's only
three טפחים tefachim away from that middle part, but it's four טפחים
tefachim away from the base. So the
גמרא Gemara continues, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר מאי טעמא משום טירייא?
mai ta'ama mishum tiraya? Why do you have to move the mill,
keep it away from the wall? Because of the vibrations, the vibrations
when they're so close will, you know, will like, like cause the
wall to become less stable. והתניא, V'hanya, but didn't we teach in
a
ברייתא, beraisa, ושל חמור ג' מן האיסטרוביל שהן ד' מן הקלת? v'shel
chamor gimel min ha'istrobiel shehein daled min hakelat? If it's a, it's
called a donkey mill, presumably because sometimes they would use donkeys to,
for in order to make it go around, but it's like a
smaller and more portable mill and that is, and similarly for that
you have to keep it away from the wall three טפחים, tefachim,
or three טפחים tefachim from the איסטרוביל istrobiel which is the bottom
part of it, which is four טפחים tefachim from the, you know,
from the upper... from the קלת kelat which is the grinding part,
which is the middle part which is more protruding, similar to the,
what do you call it? similar to the general mill. I, I
might have misstated a little bit before. Let me just repeat that.
Okay, it is the normal mill, מרחיקין את הריחיים ג' מן השכב,
marchikin es harechayim gimel min hashechev, three טפחים tefachim away from the
base of the mill which protrudes more, שהן ד' מן הרכב, shehein
daled min harechev, which is four from the part that's רכב rochev
on it, from the part that, you know, does the grinding, and
that is less, that's not as wide as the base. So something
that is three טפחים tefachim away from the base is four טפחים
tefachim away from the grinding part. And the same is true here
by the donkey mill. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, let's just
read again, מאי טעמא משום טירייא, mai ta'ama mishum tiraya, because of
the
vibrations. והתניא, V'hanya, ושל חמור, v'shel chamor, this donkey
mill, ג' מן האיסטרוביל, gimel min ha'istrobiel, three טפחים tefachim away from
the base, שהן ד' מן הקלת, shehein daled min hakelat, which is
four טפחים tefachim away from the grinding part. These are just the
different names of them. So התם, hasam, so מאי טירייא איכא? mai
tiraya ika? So okay it's... So okay, it's the exact same law
as a normal mill, but if it's about vibrations, that's a very
portable and less weighty and it doesn't cause vibrations, so why do
you have to keep it away? אלא משום קלא, ella mishum kala,
fine, it's not vibrations, it's because of the sound. It's very noisy
and the sound waves, you know, impact the wall if it's too
close. וכן תנור שלש מן הכליה שהן ארבע מן השפה, ve-chen tannur
shalosh min ha-kalya she-hein arba min ha-safa, and a similarly the, you
know, the what do you call it, an oven is four from
three from the base, which is four from the from the mouth
of the oven. The oven basically looked like just a large pot
and the base was larger, you know, than the top, than the
mouth at the opening. תוספות Tosafot actually says that it's somewhat of
like, you know, what are those called pot-belly stoves where it's narrow
at the top, wide in the middle, then narrow again at the
bottom. So the three טפחים tefachim is away from the bump in
the middle and the four טפחים tefachim from the mouth. רש"י Rashi
says it's just a case more of, you know, wide bottom and
and like a beaker, wide bottom and a narrow top, and it's
three from the bottom and four from the
top. אמר אביי שמע מינא כליה דתנור טפח. amar Abaye shema mina
kalya de-tannur tefach. We hear from this that the כליה, kalya, the
base of the תנור, tannur, protrudes a טפח, tefach, or for תוספות,
Tosafot, the middle, the pot-belly part of the oven protrudes a
טפח. tefach. נפקא מינה למקח וממכר, nafka mina le-mekkach u-mimkar, and the
relevance is for a business. Somebody would have a right to complain
if you agreed to make them an oven or sell them an
oven and it did not have that wide of a base. Okay,
so that is the end of that משנה mishna about the things
that you have to distance from the wall because of the concern
that they'll damage the wall and then the really important discussion in
the גמרא Gemara about אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, the whole discussion
the other day about if you're if you're the first one there,
do you also have to distance yourself from the boundary line with
the anticipation that, because otherwise you're force, you know, you're not allowing
the other person to do something because you got there first? You
have to anticipate that and also remove yourself from the boundary line,
or is it sort of, no, you get there first and then
it's the other person's responsibility to keep away? And then a really
central debate of רבי, Rabbi, of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the
חכמים Chachamim about על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו או על הניזק להרחיק
את עצמו. al ha-mazzik le-harchik et atzmo o al ha-nizzak le-harchik et
atzmo. Who has to do the distancing? If you're you know does
is it the one that is doing the damage which you would
think, or do you say, no, I'm just doing whatever I want
in my own yard, which is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says.
You don't, that's something that's going to negatively impact you, you have
to go ahead and distance yourself. Okay, so those seem to be
different ways of determining who has the responsibility, and that we dealt
with before, but that is the central issue of this פרק. perek.
Let's see the next משנה. mishna. לא יעמיד אדם תנור בתוך הבית
אלא אם כן יש על גביו גובה ארבע אמות. lo ya'amid adam
tannur be-toch ha-bayit ella im ken yesh al gabav govah arba amot.
Okay, so this is sort of like a fire code, but it's
also a responsibility to your neighbor because assuming that you have a
house and that somebody is in the top story and you're at
the bottom story, so you should not have an oven in your
house unless there is a four אמות, amot, which is like six
feet between the opening of the oven of the top of the
oven and the ceiling. Otherwise, we're afraid that it'll be too too
close and that it'll, you know, and that the steam and the
heat, whatever, will, you know, will will will damage the ceiling and
also, of course, so that, you know, it should not be a
fire hazard. Okay. אלא אם כן יש על גביו גובה ארבע אמות.
ella im ken yesh al gabav govah arba amot. היה מעמידו בעליה,
haya ma'amido be-aliya, now let's say you were actually in the second
story and you wanted your
oven. צריך שיהא תחתיו מעזיבה שלשה טפחים. tzarich she-ye-hei tachtav ma'aziva shelosha
tefachim. You have to have three טפחים tefachim of plaster on the
wall, what's your what's your floor and the bottom guy's ceiling similarly
in order so that it does not, you know, the heat does
not undermine the stability of the floor and then start a fire
or have the oven come crashing through. Okay. And obviously on and
obviously also for the guy in the second story, you need to
have four אמות amot between the top of the oven and the
ceiling. היה מעמידו בעליה צריך שיהא תחתיו מעזיבה שלשה טפחים. haya ma'amido
be-aliya tzarich she-ye-hei tachtav ma'aziva shelosha tefachim. ובכירה טפח. u-ve-khira tefach. If
you are dealing with a כירה, kireh, which is a smaller sized
oven, this is very relevant for שבת, Shabbat, we won't go into
the details here, but then it is sufficient that you only have
one טפח tefach of plaster underneath it. Sounds like you would still
need the what do you call it, the same amount on top
of it. But רש"י Rashi says that because it is smaller, you
don't what do you call it, because it is smaller, you don't
make as big of a fire, like imagine different burners on your
oven. So since you don't make as big of a fire, that's
also the reason why we are being more lenient, although again you
would want to know that a should that then logically affect the
question of its distance from the ceiling, although the משנה mishna is
not saying
that. Okay. ואם היזיק משלם מה שהיזיק. ve-im hizzik meshalem mah she-hizzik.
Even when you follow this this code, if it damages at the
end of the day, you're liable. It's still your fire that is
causing
damage. רבי שמעון אומר לא אמרו כל השיעורים האלו אלא שאם היזיק
פטור מלשלם. Rabbi Shimon omer lo amru kol ha-shi'urim ha-elu ella she-im
hizzik patur mi-leshalem. You know, no, they only said these שיעורים, shi'urim,
they gave you this amount to say that then you've done your
responsibility and then you would be exempt. So this really gets us
into fascinating בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, you know, area because because normally,
right, you have an obligation to watch your fire, which is essentially
what this is, that it doesn't go out and, you know, and
spread into the neighbor's yard. And if you do your job of
watching your fire, then you're not liable. So, you know, aren't these
amounts the amounts of watching it? So what's the logic of the
חכמים? Chachamim? You certainly understand רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position. What's the
logic of the חכמים, Chachamim, of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that
says that you're still liable? So, you know, one way to answer
this is is that it's really not considered sufficient שמירה. shemirah. But
we have to allow you to have, you know, reasonable way in
which to live. So can, you know, does our desire to give
you more freedom to live like, you know, maybe the שמירה shemirah
would have to be twenty feet on top of it to really
be considered sufficient? But we're going to say you you know you're
not completely getting yourself out of all liability when you do it,
but we'll say it'll be sufficient for general operating purposes because because
to demand that you completely protect yourself from liability would not be
livable. So that's interesting question. And you have this tension in בבא
קמא, Bava Kamma, you know, between the idea of רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. A number of ראשונים Rishonim say, why is an animal that
eats and stomps on things in רשות הרבים reshut harabim exempt? Because
if you would make you liable, nobody would use רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. So the things that happen naturally, you have to not make
them liable in order so that they can live their lives. And
here it's like a middle state. Like it's enough that people will
still make fires and people need to make fires. So we don't
have to say you have no liability. We there will be liability
because you're not fully protecting the fire, and at the same time,
we're going to allow you to do it so you can live
your life. That seems to be what's going on for
the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Okay. לא יפתח אדם חנות של נחתומים
ושל צבעים תחת אוצרו של חברו. Lo yiftach adam chanut shel nachtomim
veshel tzeva'im tachat otzaro shel chavero. We had this quoted before. A
person should not open up a bakery and a store and a
and a dyeing, a place for doing dyes, under somebody else's storehouse
because the fumes and the smoke and whatever will go up and
it will ruin the person's, you know, wheat or straw or whatever
the person is storing
there, fruit. ולא רפת בקר. Velo refet bakar. And also not a
like a stable, well stable's for horses, a what do you call
it? A place in which you keep the cows. Obviously, that's really
stinky. באמת ביין התירו אבל לא רפת בקר. Be'emet beyayin hitiru aval
lo refet bakar. Actually, when you're keeping in your storehouse wine, it's
permissible. The smoke the the the smell, you know, from the bakery
and from the dyeing place actually doesn't hurt the wine, but a
place where you keep your cows, a cowshed, I guess is what
it would be called, that is not allowed. Okay. ותניא, Ve-tanya, said
the גמרא, Gemara, בתנור ארבע בכירה שלוש. be-tannur arba be-kirah shalosh. Now,
our
ברייתא braita says that when it is a when you're dealing with
the amount of plaster on the second story, if it's a תנור,
tannur, you need four טפחים tefachim of plaster, and כירה kirah three.
Our משנה mishnah said three for תנור tannur and one for
כירה. kirah. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, כי תניא ההיא בנחתומים. ki
tanya ha-hi be-nachtomim. We're talking there about a baker's oven, you know,
like we would we would have like a pizza oven, like a
very, you know, big oven. And therefore it would be much larger,
and their תנורים tannurim would be bigger and their כירות kirot would
be bigger, and therefore it's different
amounts. דתנור דידן ככירה דנחתומים. De-tannur didan ke-kirah de-nachtomim. Our תנור tannur
which requires three טפחים tefachim is the same size as a כירה
kirah for a baker, okay? And that was and therefore the כירה
kirah for a baker is three טפחים tefachim and the and the
תנור tannur for a baker is four טפחים. tefachim. All right. לא
יפתח חנות. Lo yiftach chanut. Now we totally skipped over the question
about the liability, which I think is probably is really interesting, that
בבא קמא Bava Kamma discussion, and we go to the end of
the משנה, mishnah, which is again the opening of the of the
of the bakery or of the
cowshed or whatever underneath the storehouse. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braita: אם הייתה רפת קודמת לאוצר מותר. Im hayta refet kodemet
le-otzar muttar. If, however, the cowshed came first, then and the guy
decides now that he's going to build a he's going to use
the top, you know, maybe somebody was just living there or I
don't know, was storing furniture there, whatever it was, and now they
decided that they want to use the second story into a place
for storing grain or storing fruit or whatever, then you don't have
to move it. You were here first. And again, we quoted this
the other day. All right. בעי אביי, Ba'ei Abaye, אביי Abaye asks:
כיבד וריבץ לאוצר מהו? Kibbed ve-ribbetz le-otzar mahu? Let's say he started
doing things to prepare that story for a for a storehouse, and
then, but it wasn't yet being used for a storehouse, and while
he was there, you know, cleaning it out and and sweeping it
out and getting it ready for that, while he was doing that...
אביי Abaye asked: כביי ורביי לא צר מהו. Kibbei u'reibbei lo tzar
mahu. Let's say he started doing things to prepare that story for
a storehouse and then, but it wasn't yet being used for a
storehouse and while he was there, cleaning it out and sweeping it
out and getting it ready for that, while he was doing that
and it was clear what his intention was, but it hadn't actually
been put to use yet for a storehouse on the second story,
you moved your cowshed into the bottom story. Is that okay? Are
you considered first, or is he considered
first? ריבא בחלונות מהו, Reiba be-chalonos mahu, let's say he actually made
structural changes, not just cleaning it out and sweeping it out. He
started opening up, you know, additional windows for air, for light, whatever
it would be that would be clearly being done in order to
use it as a
storehouse. אכסדרה תחת האוצר מהו, Achsadra tachas ha-otzar mahu, now that seems
not related to the questions at all and the ב"ח Bach takes
that line out so we'll skip that. בנה עליה גבי בית מהו,
Bana aliya gabei bayis mahu, or let's say, you know, you had
the bottom house, you know, bottom story, and you weren't yet using,
you know, you had a house. You weren't using it yet for
a cowshed and then you sold somebody the rights to, you know,
to go ahead and build a second story on it and they
built a second story and it was for the purpose of, you
know, using it as a storehouse, but they hadn't started using it
as a storehouse. So, different degrees: one is just sweeping, one is
making structural changes, one is even building it. Is that considered that
the storehouse was there first and you can't move in your cowshed,
or is the storehouse not there yet and you can do the
cowshed and call dibs? So the גמרא Gemara says: תיקו, Teiku, we
don't know. Okay, בעי רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: Ba'ei Rav Huna
brei de-Rav Yehoshua: תמרי ורימוני מאי, Tamrei ve-rimonei mai, what about if
you're using it for something like dates and pomegranates, which would not
be as affected presumably by the smells from below? Would that also
have the same הלכה? halacha? תיקו, Teiku, we let that stand, we
don't know. Okay, באמת ביין התירו, be-emes be-yayin hitiru, in truth they
allowed it for
wine. תנא: Tana: ביין התירו מפני שמשביחו, be-yayin hitiru mipnei she-mashpicho, by
wine they permitted it because actually the fumes from the bakery or
whatever, you know, improve the wine. I get it from a bakery,
I don't know about the chemical fumes from a dyeing, but I
don't know what's involved in
dyeing wool. ולא רפת בקר מפני שמסריחו, ve-lo refes bakar mipnei she-masricho,
but it's still not a cowshed because that will spoil it. אמר
רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: האי דידן אפילו קוטרא דשרגא נמי קשה
ליה, Hai didan afilu kutra de-sharga nami kasha lei, you know, with
our wine it's more vulnerable, you know, less, and therefore even the
smoke of a, from a candle will actually be bad for it,
so you have to be super careful with wine and there's no
more latitude with
wine. אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshes: אספסתא כרפת בקר דמיא. Aspasta
ke-refes bakar damya. And אספסתא, aspasta, which I think is vetch, which
is a type of a thing that they would feed to animals,
if you wanted to store that in the bottom story, that also
has such a stinky smell, that's just like the case of the
cowshed. Okay, we will end with this here.